Dunham Family Papers, 1814-1951
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Dunham family papers
1814-1951 [ongoing]
1855-1951
Dunham family
MS 246
57 boxes (20 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Artist, photographer, homemaker, traveler, philanthropist, bacteriologist, pathologist, and financier. The Dunham Family Papers represent four generations of the Dunham, Parker, Kellogg, and Dows families. The collection documents the medical education, research and professional activities of doctors Carroll Dunham and Edward Kellogg Dunham, Jr.; the financial activities of Edward Kellogg Dunham Jr.; the World War I medical and the volunteer work of women, including Theodora Dunham Bodman; creative writings; artwork; numerous photographs; travel correspondence; diaries and photographs from Europe, Egypt, the western U.S., and Panama.
The Dunham family as represented in this collection begins with Edward Wood Dunham (1794-1871) of New Brunswick, New Jersey, and his wife, Maria Smyth Parker (1794-1834), of Perth Amboy, New Jersey. They moved to New York City in 1821. There Edward established himself as a banker and eventually became president of the Corn Exchange Bank. Edward and Maria Dunham had four children: Ann Lawrence, Edward, James, and Carroll.
Carroll Dunham (1828-1877) was a homeopathic physician and dean of faculty at the New York Homeopathic Medical College. He was also president of the American Institute of Homeopathy. In 1853, Carroll married Harriet E. Kellogg (1828-1878), the daughter of Edward and Esther Kellogg of Brooklyn, New York. They lived in Irvington, New York, and had six children: Carroll, Edward Kellogg, Theodore, Herbert, Constantine, and Beatrice. Herbert and Constantine both died before one year. Harriet's sister, Amelia Nash (Kellogg) Henshaw--affectionately called "Aunt Rabbit," studied under artist Samuel Colman (Anne Lawrence Dunham's husband). Beatrice Dunham was a prolific writer of stories and verses. She and other family members also compiled a family magazine called "The Phoenix."
Edward Kellogg Dunham (1860-1922) was well known for his work in the fields of pathology and bacteriology. He earned his medical degree from Harvard Medical School in 1886 then studied for a period at Koch's laboratory in Berlin where he discovered the "cholera-red" reaction. After returning to the United States, he worked for the Board of Health Commission in Boston and later became professor of pathology at the Bellevue Medical College of New York University. During World War I, he worked in U.S. Army hospitals, researching and treating meningitis cases. Soon he became involved in treating soldiers infected with empyema (a lung disease related to pneumonia) and in 1918 was appointed chairman of the "Empyema Commission." After Edward's death his empyema research was published by his wife, Mary (Dows) Dunham, and several of his colleagues. In 1923 Mary gave an endowment to Harvard Medical School for the establishment of the "Edward Kellogg Dunham Lectures for the Promotion of the Medical Sciences."
In 1893 Edward married Mary Dows (1865-1936), daughter of David Dows (1814-1890) and Margaret (Worcester) Dows (1831-1909), also of Irvington, N.Y. David Dows headed the New York firm, David Dows and Company, one of the largest grain dealers in the country. He also served on the Board of Directors of Chicago, Rock Island and Pacific Railway Co. Mary was stricken with polio as a child and was left partially disabled. She suffered from almost constant pain throughout her life, nevertheless, traveled extensively and pursued various artistic and philanthropic activities. Mary became interested in photography at a young age and was encouraged in her endeavors by artist Samuel Colman (Anne Lawrence Dunham's husband). She traveled to the western United States and Europe numerous times before her marriage to Edward in 1893. Mary and Edward traveled together in Europe, Egypt, and the Western U.S. from the 1890s to the 1910s. In Egypt, they journeyed down the Nile River on a houseboat for three weeks in 1906.
Edward and Mary had two children: Theodora Dunham (1895-1983) and Edward Kellogg Dunham, Jr. (1901-1951). Soon after the birth of their daughter Theodora, Edward and Mary moved from Litchfield, Connecticut, to New York City. In 1898 they built a house in Seal Harbor, Maine, which they named "Keewaydin." The Dows family had spent many summers in Seal Harbor and several of Mary's siblings also made it their summer home.
During World War I, Mary and Theodora were involved with the American Fund for French Wounded (AFFW), an organization which provided medical and material aid to wounded soldiers and refugees. Theodora went to France to work as a volunteer at the front from 1916 to 1917. Mary organized volunteers in both New York City and in Seal Harbor to send relief packages overseas for the AFFW workers there to distribute to refugees and soldiers.
During the early twentieth century, Mary and Edward were involved in various philanthropic activities in New York and Seal Harbor. They worked with the New York Cooking School and several New York City hospitals to establish a cooking school for nurses with the aim of improving hospital food service. In Seal Harbor, Edward tested the milk of the local dairy farms, and Edward and Mary helped to organize the Mount Desert Chapter of the American Red Cross for which both Mary and Edward Dunham, Jr., were board members. The family was also active in the Seal Harbor Village Improvement Society.
Edward Kellogg Dunham, Jr. (1901-1951), was graduated from Harvard University in 1922, and worked as assistant manager for the Corn Exchange Bank (his great-grandfather's institution) in New York through the 1920s. After that, much of his time was occupied with other financial activities as treasurer of Dows Estates (established with the estate of his grandparents) and as trustee of his mother's estate. Edward lived for a few years in the western United States where, in 1933, he met and married Anne ("Nancy") Yellott. Edward and Nancy had two children: Edward Kellogg Dunham III and Elizabeth Dunham. They eventually moved to New York City and spent their summers in Seal Harbor where Edward continued in his parents' philanthropic footsteps.
The Dunham Family Papers are a diverse collection of material documenting the personal and professional activities of four generations of the Dunham, Kellogg and Dows families from 1814 to 1951. The bulk of the material dates from 1855 to 1951. About three quarters of the collection is material relating to Mary Dows Dunham, her husband, Edward Kellogg Dunham, and their son, Edward Kellogg Dunham, Jr. The remaining quarter of the collection represents other family members.
There is a large amount of material documenting the professional and other activities of the Dunhams. Edward Kellogg Dunham, Sr.'s, papers include correspondence; lecture notes and papers from Harvard Medical School; notes from his cholera research; research material, manuscripts, and published writings relating to antiseptics and empyema during World War I. There are also letters to Mary (Dows) Dunham, written after Edward's death, from his many friends and colleagues regarding the publication of his research on empyema and the establishment of the Edward Kellogg Dunham Lectures at Harvard Medical School. Additional papers related to the Dunham Lectures are located at the Francis A. Countway Library of Medicine at Harvard.
Mary (Dows) Dunham's papers document her and Edward Dunham's various philanthropic activities during the early twentieth century, including the New York cooking school for nurses, the American Red Cross, and the Seal Harbor Village Improvement Society. There is also material relating to Mary and Theodora Dunham's work with the American Fund for French Wounded which includes letters from American and French soldiers, relief workers, nurses, and doctors stationed in World War I France.
Edward Kellogg Dunham, Jr.'s, Mount Desert Island material provides valuable information on the development of a rural seaside community. It includes correspondence; reports and minutes of committee meetings; and clippings and photographic material. These date from 1930 to 1949.
The Dunham Family Papers include correspondence and other material relating to a number of important individuals, most notably medical and academic colleagues of Edward Kellogg Dunham, Sr. These are located in the papers of Edward Kellogg Dunham, Sr., Mary (Dows) Dunham, and Edward Kellogg Dunham, Jr. Important correspondents include: Walter B. Cannon, physiologist; Samuel Colman, artist; Henry D. Dakin, English chemist and brother-in-law of EKD and MDD; D.L. Edsall, Dean, Harvard Medical School; Simon Flexner, pathologist; Graham Lusk, physiologist; John D. Rockefeller, Jr., philanthropist; Henry Osborne Taylor, author; William S. Thayer, M.D.; John L. Yates, surgeon.
A significant portion of the material consists of personal correspondence. Of particular interest are the travel letters of Harriet (Kellogg) Dunham to her family from Italy (1855-56), and Mary (Dows) Dunham to her mother from her various travels in the western United States, Bermuda, Europe, Greece, and Egypt dating from 1877 to 1914. These trips are particularly well detailed in Mary's letters which are complimented by her numerous photographs (located at the end of the collection).
Throughout the collection there are creative writings of various individuals, in particular, those of Harriet (Kellogg) Dunham, Beatrice Dunham, and Mary (Dows) Dunham. Carroll and Harriet Dunham, their children, and friends created a magazine called "The Phoenix" which consisted of articles, stories, poems, and artwork periodically compiled together and distributed to family and friends. They maintained and distributed this family magazine from 1883 to 1888.
A large portion of the collection is photographic material (prints, negatives, and photograph albums) including images of Europe, Egypt, Greece, Central America, the Caribbean, and the western United States, and ranging in date from the 1890s to the 1930s. There are also prints and many negatives of family, friends, and activities on Mount Desert Island, ca. 1910 to 1930. Many of the images are in negative format only.
The collection also includes genealogies, family histories, biographical material, legal documents, financial records, printed pamphlets, clippings, and memorabilia.
The collection is arranged by individual or, where there is only a small amount of material, by family. These are the family papers of each of the three women who married Dunham men: Maria Smythe (Parker) Dunham, Harriet (Kellogg) Dunham, and Mary (Dows) Dunham. The family papers of each woman precede her own papers. The individuals and families are, in most cases, in order by generation. Material under each individual is arranged by type. Some photographs are filed with the papers if their subject content is specifically related to that material. However, the bulk of the photographic images (prints and negatives) are filed separately, at the end of the papers. Photographs of individuals are arranged alphabetically. Other photographs and negatives are arranged by subject. Oversize items are located in the oversize boxes at the end of the collection or in the flat file. These are cross-referenced in the inventory and by separation sheets which are filed throughout the collection.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Additional Formats
Selections from the Dunham Family Papers can be viewed in the Web exhibit Across the Generations: Exploring U.S. History through Family Papers.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected.
History of the Collection
The Dunham Family Papers were given to the Sophia Smith Collection by Herbert Luther Bodman, Jr., and Ellen-Fairbanks Diggs Bodman in 1985. The material was initially part of a larger collection of papers relating to both the Bodman and Dunham families. They are now organized as two separate collections.
Search Terms
Bodman, Theodora Dunham, 1895-1983; Cannon, Walter Bradford, 1871-1945--Correspondence; Colman, Samuel--Correspondence; Dakin, Henry Drysdale, 1880- --Correspondence; Dunham, Beatrice, 1870-1911; Dunham, Edward Wood, 1794-1871; Dunham, Carroll, 1828-1877; Dunham, Mary Dows, 1865-1938; Dunham, Edward Kellogg, 1860-1922; Dunham, Edward Kellogg, 1901-1951; Dunham, Harriet Elvira Kellogg, 1820-1905; Edsall, D.L.; Jacobson, C. A. (Carl Alfred), 1876-1956; Rockefeller, John Davison, 1874-1960--Correspondence; Taylor, Henry Osborne, 1856-1941--Correspondence; Flexner, Simon, 1863-1946--Correspondence; Thayer, William Sydney, 1864-1932--Correspondence; Lusk, Graham, 1866-1932--Correspondence; Yates, John L., 1873-1938--Correspondence; Bodman family; Dows family; Dunham family; Kellogg family; Parker family--Genealogy; American Fund for French Wounded--History; American Red Cross. Mount Desert Island (Me.)--History--Sources; Harvard Medical School--History--Sources; Europe--Description and travel--Sources; Children's writings, American; Empyema--Research--Sources; Family--United States--History--Sources; Medicine--Research--United States--History--Sources; Nursing schools--History--New York (State)--New York; Pathology--Research--History--Sources; Philanthropists--United States--History--Sources; Public health nursing--History--Mount Desert Island (Me); Upper class families--United States--History--Sources; Voyages and travel--History--Sources; Women artists--United States--History--20th century--Sources; World War, 1914-1918--Medical care--France--Personal narratives; World War, 1914-1918--Medical care--United States--Sources; World War, 1914-1918--War work - France--Sources; Egypt--Description and travel--Sources; Europe--Description and travel--Sources; Italy--Description and travel--Sources; Mount Desert Island (Me)--History--Sources; Panama--Description and travel--Sources; United States--Social life and customs--19th century--Sources; United States--Social life and customs--20th century--Sources; West (U.S.)--Description and travel--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
See also the Bodman Family Papers. Researchers should note that there is material related to the Dunham and Bodman families in both collections and that there are cross-references to the Bodman Family Papers throughout the Dunham Family Papers inventory. The papers of Theodora (Dunham) Bodman are mostly located in the Bodman Family Papers except for her correspondence to her parents (filed under Mary Dows Dunham).
- General Family Histories and Genealogies
  - Genealogical charts, compiled 1993 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Dunham-Parker Genealogy (typed copy of mss. by A.E. Parker), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Dunham-Parker Genealogy (same as above with revisions), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dows-Kellogg-Dunham genealogy: correspondence, notes, 1929-32, 1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Parker family history: notes compiled by A.E. Parker, ca. 1882 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Historical pamphlets by Charles Parker, 1929, 1931, 1932, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dunham Name List, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dows Family history: correspondence, pamphlet, clippings, 1856, 1920 1924, 1932, 1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dows Family history: pamphlet, clippings, 1924, 1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence between Mary (Dows) Dunham and the Metropolitan Museum of Art regarding Kellogg portraits, 1922-23, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clippings: Walcott Dunham and Warner relative, 1966, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photographs of cemetery headstones, 1926, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cemetery maps, headstone drawings and rubbing [for Harriet (Kellogg) Dunham stone], undated (Box 1)
    [see Oversize material, Flat file]
- Gertrude Ann Parker (1789-1862)
  - Commonplace book, 1834-1861 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence from Carroll Dunham, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence to aunt [?], undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Edward Wood Dunham (1794-1871)
  - Biographical: "History of the Corn Exchange Bank: 1852-1928 " (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: E. Littell, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Financial
    - Account Book, 1853-70 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Estate journals, 1869-77 (Box 3, Folder 4-6)
    - Checkbook stubs, 1871 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Maria Smythe (Parker) Dunham (1794-1834)
  - Commonplace book and inserts, 1823-28 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
- Carroll Dunham, Sr. (1828-1877)
  - Biographical: "Anecdotes of Carroll Dunham, written by his wife, Harriet E. K. Dunham," undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Writings, personal
    [see also Dunham Family Writings, boxes 9 and 10]
    - Stories, verses, 1851, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - "The Similibus," (articles by Carroll & Harriet (Kellogg) Dunham), 1872 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, family
    - Ann Lawrence (Dunham) Colman, 1867, 1874, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Samuel Colman, 1874 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Edward Wood Dunham, 1855-56, 1866-67, undated (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
    - Edward Dunham, Jr., 1855, 1866 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - A. E. (Gertrude) Parker, 1855, 1857, 1867, 1878 (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
    - Mary E. (Kellogg) Putnam, 1858 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Other family (fragments), 1855, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, general, 1855-56, 1875-76 (Box 4, Folder 13-14)
    [See also Carroll and Harriet (Kellogg) Dunham: Scrapbook of correspondence, ca. 1850-70, in Oversize material, box 56]
  - Professional Activities
    - New York Homeopathic Convention: Valedictory Address, 1872 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - World Homeopathic Convention: addresses, reports, miscellaneous, 1874-76 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Medical notes, 1872 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Financial
    - Travel expenses - Italy, 1855 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Scrapbook of receipts and financial correspondence, 1788, 1841-80 (Box 4)
      [see Oversize material, box 56]
  - Memorabilia
    - Political flyer, calling cards, lock of hair, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Memorial scroll -"Resolutions on the death of Carroll Dunham," 1877 (Box 4)
      [see also Oversize material, box 56]
- Kellogg Family
  - Ephraim Kellogg (date unknown): framed will, 1814 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Family writings (typed copies), 1847, 1866-67, 1870, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    [see also "Writings" under individuals]
  - Edward Kellogg (1790-1858) and Esther Fenn (Warner) Kellogg (1794-1872)
    - Correspondence
      - Harriet E. (Kellogg) Dunham, 1855-56, undated (Box 5, Folder 3-5)
      - Edward Kellogg Dunham, 1867 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Legal: Edward Kellogg's will, 1857 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Edward R. Kellogg, Jr. (dates unknown): will, 1858 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Mary E. (Kellogg) Putnam (dates unknown)
    - Writings, 1844 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence: Harriet (Kellogg) and Carroll Dunham, 1850, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Legal
      - Will and codicils, 1896, 1899, 1900 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Estate assignment, 1871 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Deed of land, 1891 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Mortagage, 1865 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Samuel Putnam (dates unknown): will, 1896 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Amelia Nash (Kellogg) Henshaw (1820-1905)
  - Biographical: obituary, 1905 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Writings
    - Verses, 1893, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Notes from art lectures by Samuel Colman, 1872-75 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Notes on art, 1877 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1878, 1904 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Legal
    - Partition papers, 1884 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Presentation of trusts to Edward K. and Carroll Dunham, 1901 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Will and codicil, 1899, 1903 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Account of proceedings of executor (Edward K. Dunham), 1905 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Inventory of estate (partial), 1905 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Memorabilia
    - Latin notebook, 1830? (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Autograph album, ca. 1830s (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Letter from Abraham Lincoln mentioning Major John Henshaw (copy), 1861 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Clippings, 1874, 1895, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Harriet E. (Kellogg) Dunham (1828-1878)
  - Writings
    - Family magazine - "Our Home," 1848 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - Stories, verses, 1866-67, 1869, 1873, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Notebooks of verses and stories, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, family
    - Carroll Dunham, 1848, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Edward Wood Dunham, 1856, 1867 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Kellogg Family (group letters to Harriet while she was in Europe), 1855-56 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Esther and Edward Kellogg, 1875, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Mary E. (Kellogg) Putnam, 1856, 1858, 1866, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Other family, 1877, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, general, 1867, 1876, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
    [see also Carroll and Harriet (Kellogg) Dunham: Scrapbook of correspondence, ca. 1850-70, in Oversize material, box 56]
  - Legal
    - Deeds, 1873, 1875 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Will, 1877 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Financial
    - Account book, 1855-57 (Box 7)
    - Account book, 1878-87 (Box 7)
    - Inserts from account books, ca. 1860-85 (Box 7, Folder 14-15)
    - Inventory of jewelry, undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Memorabilia
    - Autograph album (blank), 1844 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Verse by C. Cooke, 1877 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Miscellaneous, 1841, undated (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Clippings, 1861, 1877 (Box 7, Folder 20)
- Beatrice Dunham (1870-1911)
  - Biographical: obituary, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Writings
    [see also Dunham Family Writings, box 9 10]
    - Diary - travels in Europe, 1891-92 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - "Stories," 1898 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - "Our Indian," undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - "An indolent gardener," undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - "Our recovered childhood," undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - "O'Grady: a sketch," undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - "A tell-tale card," undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - "Vegetable garden," undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - untitled, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - "Aunt Rabbit: a lover of animals", 1908 (bound volume printed 1923) (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - "Verses," undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous writings, 1883, 1891 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence
    - Mary (Dows) Dunham (from Europe), 1891 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - M.L. ("Dorothea") Tincker, 1889, 1896, undated (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Legal
    - Will, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Proceedings of executor of estate (Edward K. Dunham), 1919 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Memorabilia: verses, 1869, 1892, undated (Box 8, Folder 18)
- Carroll Dunham, Jr. (1858-1922): correspondence, 1866, 1879 (Box 8, Folder 19)
- Dunham Family Writings, [see also "Writings" under individuals and Oversize Material - Scrapbook of writings by EKD and CD, Jr.]
  - Family magazine - "Tanglewood Twigs," 1872 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous writings for family magazine
    - Beatrice Dunham, 1885 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Carroll Dunham, Sr., undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Carroll Dunham, Jr., 1877 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Edward Kellogg Dunham, 1877 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Theodore Dunham, 1877 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Florence Perkins Benedict, 1877 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Edmund Augustus Benedict, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Fragments by unknown authors, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Family magazine - "The Phoenix"
    - Resolutions, minutes, constitution (for "The Spree Club"), 1885 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Letters to the editor, 1885-87, undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous writings for "The Phoenix," 1884-85, undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Series I, 1883-85 (Box 9, Folder 13-29)
    - Series II, 1885-86 (Box 10, Folder 1-9)